<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>Hemish - List of poems</title>
	<link href="https://hemish.tk/poems/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://hemish.tk/poems/"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://hemish.tk/poems/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>बेनाम शहर</title>
		<published>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://hemish.tk/poems/benaam-shahar/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://hemish.tk/poems/benaam-shahar/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;pre&gt;
मेरा जीवन एक किताब है,
इसे सम्पन्न करने का मेरा ख्वाब है।
जानता हूँ इसमें बहुत सारे दाग हैं,
पर इन्हें साफ़ करने के लिए भी कोई ना कोई आब है। &lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;pre&gt;
कमाए हमने बहुत सारे खिताब हैं,
और भी कमाने की आग है।
इस &#x27;नई दुनिया&#x27; का हिस्सा बनने का ख्वाब है।
बस यही ज़िन्दगी एक नाव है।

ज़िन्दगी जीनी नहीं बेकाम है,
करने अभी बहुत सारे काम हैं।
अभी तो ज़िन्दगी बस एक गाम (गाँव) है,
जो शहर ये बनेगी वो अभी बेनाम है।
&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>ए मक्षिका! क्या भिनभिनाती हो?</title>
		<published>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://hemish.tk/poems/e-makshika/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://hemish.tk/poems/e-makshika/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A little bit of background, how I came up with this poem:
We had a poem in Grade 9 in school (it was in क्षितिज NCERT book), titled &amp;quot;कैदी और कोकिला&amp;quot; which (you can read it &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.hindipyala.com&#x2F;kaidi-aur-kokila&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) had  primary lines &amp;quot;क्या गाती हो&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;कोकिल बोलो तो&amp;quot;. It was hightly metaphorical poem, and was written by Makhanlal Chaturvedi during his stay in jail during India&#x27;s Independence moment. Our teacher Meena Anand ma&#x27;am asked us to write one such poem in that style, so I came up with this poem titled &amp;quot;ए मक्षिका! क्या भिनभिनाती हो?&amp;quot;. Is it weird, or is it funny, or does it have some deep message (I seriously did not intend to give a deep message, but if you are a hardcore poet, maybe let me know about the deep meaning.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here it is:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
क्या भिनभिनाती हो? क्या कहना चाहती हो?
क्यूँ ईधर-उधर घूमती जाती हो? मुझे बताओ!
यूँ suspense ना बनाओ!

क्या तुम भी बोर होकर ही, भिनभिना रही हो?
क्यूँ झूटे खा रही हो? क्या तुम हमारे जीवन की,
रोज़मर्रा की प्रतिक्रियाएँ ही करना चाह रही हो?

तुम्हारा यह &#x27;भिन्न-भिन्न&#x27; मुझे और सुनओ,
या फ़िर अपना मकसद बताओ!
क्यूँ तुम ईधर-उधर घूमती जाती हो?
क्या मुझे कुछ बताना चाह रही हो?
कहाँ है तुम्हारा ईशारा, या फिर सिर्फ़ भिनभिनाहट का गीत प्यारा!
&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>ਜਾਣਨਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹਾਂ</title>
		<published>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://hemish.tk/poems/jaanna-chahunda-haan/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://hemish.tk/poems/jaanna-chahunda-haan/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;pre&gt;
ਮੈਂ ਖਾਸ ਹਾਂ,
ਇਹ ਮੈਂ ਜਾਣਦਾ ਹਾਂ,
ਤੇ ਏਸੇ ਖਾਸ ਖੁਦ ਨੂੰ ,
ਪਛਾਣਨਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹਾਂ।&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;pre&gt;
ਕੀ ਹਾਂ ਮੈਂ ,
ਕੀ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਪਸੰਦ ਹੈ,
ਕੀ ਕਰਨਾ ਹੈ ਮੈਂ,
ਤੇ ਮੇਰਾ ਕੀ ਮਕਸਦ ਹੈ?

ਕੌਣ ਹਾਂ ਮੈਂ,
ਇਹ ਜਾਣਨਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹਾਂ,
ਤਾਰਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਹਨੇਰੇ &#x27;ਚ,
ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਸੋਚਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹਾਂ।

ਕੀ ਕਰਨਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹਾਂ,
ਕੀ ਪਾਉਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹਾਂ,
ਕੀ ਖੋਹਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹਾਂ,
ਤੇ ਕਿਹੋ ਜਿਹੀ ਜ਼ਿੰਦਗੀ ਜਿਉਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹਾਂ।
&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Talents and qualities of my classmates</title>
		<published>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://hemish.tk/poems/talents-and-qualities-of-my-classmates/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://hemish.tk/poems/talents-and-qualities-of-my-classmates/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In Grade 10, during the period where studies were semi-online (lockdown was just opened, and we started going to school for reduced hours optionally), our English teacher Sujata ma&#x27;am provided us with projects we have to do for final evaluation. One of these was to write a song on the topic &amp;quot;Talents and qualities of my classmates&amp;quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While she never clarified her motive of assigning this topic, but according to me, her motive was to clear: make us realise that on-campus education has one advantage that is friends. The idea of &amp;quot;writing a song&amp;quot; was new to most students in class. To be honest, I don&#x27;t even know a single person in my section who actually wrote one, maybe some wrote but they never talked to me, atleast neither of my friends wrote any song, they just copied random poems from the Internet and sang them, some even asked to copy mine (referring to you Swayam), but no poem was found on Internet with such niche topic &#x27;Talents and qualities of my classmates&#x27;, so they ended up finding poems with topics like &#x27;friends&#x27;, &#x27;qualities of my friends&#x27;. The idea to write a poem on such niche topic was also perplexing for me, but anyhow I ended up writing one good poem which my teacher liked. So here it is:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
The class 10 students are not bad, and would help whosoever is sad.
They would make a sad one laugh, and most of them obey the staff.
Some of them are good at computers, and may be good programmers.
Be it powerpoint or excel, every computer problem they smell.
Some of them are good at writing, their writings are so exciting.
They write articles and poems, be they about rain or storms.
Many of them are good at study, and act like a true buddy.
They always answer the questions, and still about aware of recent fashions.
Some of them are good at dance, but need to prepare in advance.
They always represent the school, and their dance is refreshing and cool
Some of them are good at singing, and as good as a bird’s chirping.
They always represent the school, and knit the music like a wool.
Some of them are good at sports, many play at basketball courts.
Some play cricket and other specials, and most always win nice medals.
Some of them are good in arts, and also make mindblowing crafts.
Their drawings are so realistic, and their formation is artistic.
Some of them are very kind, and such people are hard to find.
Many of them are caring, and are so much protective.
They all are so much talented, and have their talents patented.
Many of them are very creative, and also co-operative.
Anyways; they are my classmates, and have their own talents and fates.
Noone is worth calling a fool, and they are my classmates at the school.
&lt;pre&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>The Blank Face</title>
		<published>2022-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://hemish.tk/poems/the-blank-face/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://hemish.tk/poems/the-blank-face/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One day I had a dream, so I wrote about it:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;pre&gt;
I like you, though I don&#x27;t know you.
You are someone in my head, the imagination I have always fed.
You are perfect, on me you have a doppler effect,
how my frequency of vibes diverge, when you are at my heart&#x27;s verge.
I like your intellect, on me it has a very special effect.
I also like your physique, with beauty at its peak.

I saw you in my dreams, I saw a blank face it seems.
How this blank face would be decoded? which is with happiness overloaded!
How would you be recognised? How would you be specified?
How would I reach you: let&#x27;s see, but please don&#x27;t flee!

I don&#x27;t know you for the sake, that you would become someone that my imagination
 would make.
You would be perfect, just the way you would be.
Your image in my mind that is kept, would deflect as need be.
You would be charming just the way you are,
I won&#x27;t mind if your face has a scar.
Don&#x27;t change yourself for me, be the authentic one you should always be.

One day this blank face would be happily filled, but I feel bad that the imagination would be killed.
&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my dream, I was with a slow dancing with a person, without music, and to my surprise, the face did not have any eyes, mouth or nose, it was simply blank (because my mind did not want to generalise anything?) Then, I have described what qualities would ideally be in such a person, but they need not be strictly correct as I said &amp;quot;your image in my mind, would deflect as need be&amp;quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
