<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>Hemish - opensource</title>
	<link href="https://hemish.tk/tags/opensource/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://hemish.tk"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2022-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://hemish.tk/tags/opensource/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Upgrading firmware in Linux using fwupd</title>
		<published>2022-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://hemish.tk/posts/fwupd/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://hemish.tk/posts/fwupd/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Want to upgrade your PC or laptop&#x27;s firmware but don&#x27;t want to use Windows?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;wiki.archlinux.org&#x2F;title&#x2F;fwupd&quot;&gt;Fwupd&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a command line program, which has the ability to fetch firmware updates from vendors (including proprietary vendors like Dell) and apply the updates.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, it worked seamlessly with my Dell Latitude 5490 and a HGST brand hard drive.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to just enable the &lt;code&gt;fwupd.service&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; through systemd, and then you would be able to operate the application using the command line.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some GUI front ends available for the same application like gnome-firmware. Even &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ubuntu.com&quot;&gt;Ubuntu&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is developing a flutter based frontend for it. But, for me, command line works best.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s just wonderful to see that we have reached a point, where every other thing doesn&#x27;t require Windows, and we can daily drive Linux on our laptops and computers. That&#x27;s the power of opensource community.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Translating in open-source world</title>
		<published>2022-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://hemish.tk/posts/localisation-credits-opensource/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://hemish.tk/posts/localisation-credits-opensource/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Isn&#x27;t it amazing to get your credits in an opensource app?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;continue-reading&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;dialect-credits.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot showing credits in app called Dialect&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dialect is an open-source desktop translation app for linux systems, specifically designed for GNOME desktop. I translated it into Hindi so that anyone using their desktop in Hindi may be able to see Hindi translations and the app doesnt look like an odd English app in hindi environment.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open-source is not only about code, it&#x27;s about multi-faceted work loads spread across community , to which everyone contributes in their own time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and this includes translation as well. We live in a globalised world, so people across different nations, speaking different languages use computers, so internationalization (i18n) and localisation (l10n) of apps is important.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I belive having access to computers is a basic right for everyone, and whatever I can do for making computers more accessible is worth it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, I am part of hindi translation team at &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;l10n.gnome.org&quot;&gt;l10n.gnome.org&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (and I have translated stuff like gnome-clocks, gnome-weather, gnome-bluetooth, gnome-characters). The official website of our team is &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;indlinux.org&quot;&gt;indlinux.org&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
